Programming Hive.pdf
CHAPTER 3
Data Types and File Formats
============================

Hive supports many of the primitive data types you find in relational databases, as well as three collection data types that are rarely found in relational databases,

Primitive Data Types
-------------------
TINYINT - 1 byte signed integer - 20
SMALLINT - 2 byte signed integer - 20
INT - 4 byte signed integer- 20
BIGINT - 8 byte signed integer - 20
BOOLEAN - Boolean true or false - TRUE
FLOAT - Single precision floating point - 3.14159
DOUBLE - Double precision floating point - 3.14159
STRING - Sequence of characters. The character
set can be specified. Single or double
quotes can be used. - 'Now is the time', "for all good men"
TIMESTAMP (v0.8.0+) - 
BINARY (v0.8.0+) - 

It’s useful to remember that each of these types is implemented in Java,For example, STRING is implemented by the Java String, FLOAT is implemented by Java float, etc.

Note that Hive does not support “character arrays” (strings).Values of the new TIMESTAMP type can be integers.

TIMESTAMPS are interpreted as UTC times. Built-in functions for conversion to and from timezones are provided by Hive, to_utc_timestamp and from_utc_timestamp, respectively

The BINARY type is similar to the VARBINARY type found in many relational databases.
It’s not like a BLOB type,

You can explicitly convert one type to another using cast function, e.g cast(s AS INT)

Collection Data Types
---------------------
Hive supports columns that are structs, maps, and arrays

STRUCT - Analogous to a C struct or an “object.” Fields can be accessed using the “dot” notation. For example, if a column name is of type STRUCT {first STRING; last STRING}, then the first name field can be referenced using name.first.

syntax - struct('John', 'Doe')

MAP - A collection of key-value tuples, where the fields are accessed using array notation (e.g., ['key']). For example, if a column name is of type MAP with key→value pairs 'first'→'John' and 'last'→'Doe', then the last name can be referenced using name['last'].

syntax - map('first', 'John', 'last', 'Doe')

ARRAY - Ordered sequences of the same type that are indexable using zero-based integers. For example, if a column name is of type ARRAY of strings with the value ['John', 'Doe'], then the second element can be referenced using name[1].

Syntax - array('John', 'Doe')

Most relational databases don’t support such collection types, because using them tends to break normal form. For example, in traditional data models, structs might be captured in separate tables, with foreign key relations between the tables, as appropriate.

A practical problem with breaking normal form is the greater risk of data duplication,leading to unnecessary disk space consumption and potential data inconsistencies.

However, in Big Data systems, a benefit of sacrificing normal form is higher processing throughput. Scanning data off hard disks with minimal “head seeks” is essential when processing terabytes to petabytes of data. Embedding collections in records makes retrieval faster with minimal seeks. Navigating each foreign key relationship requires seeking across the disk, with significant performance overhead

Table declaration syntax
------------------------

CREATE TABLE employees (
name STRING,
salary FLOAT,
subordinates ARRAY<STRING>,
deductions MAP<STRING, FLOAT>,
address STRUCT<street:STRING, city:STRING, state:STRING, zip:INT>);

Below is the sample file.

John Doe^A100000.0^AMary Smith^BTodd Jones^AFederal Taxes^C.2^BState Taxes^C.05^BInsurance^C.1^A1 Michigan Ave.^BChicago^BIL^B60600

Mary Smith^A80000.0^ABill King^AFederal Taxes^C.2^BState Taxes^C.05^BInsurance^C.1^A100 Ontario St.^BChicago^BIL^B60601

Todd Jones^A70000.0^AFederal Taxes^C.15^BState Taxes^C.03^BInsurance^C.1^A200 Chicago Ave.^BOak Park^BIL^B60700

Bill King^A60000.0^AFederal Taxes^C.15^BState Taxes^C.03^BInsurance^C.1^A300 Obscure Dr.^BObscuria^BIL^B60100

In above sample file data, Columns are separated by ^A(001), ARRAY or STRUCT elements are separated by ^B(002) and map elements are separated by ^C(003)

Below is the json representation of above data.

{
"name": "John Doe",
"salary": 100000.0,
"subordinates": ["Mary Smith", "Todd Jones"],
"deductions": {
"Federal Taxes": .2,
"State Taxes": .05,
"Insurance": .1
},
"address": {
"street": "1 Michigan Ave.",
"city": "Chicago",
"state": "IL",
"zip": 60600
}
}
You’ll note that

Here is the same table declaration
again, this time with all the format defaults explicitly specified:
CREATE TABLE employees (
name STRING,
salary FLOAT,
subordinates ARRAY<STRING>,
deductions MAP<STRING, FLOAT>,
address STRUCT<street:STRING, city:STRING, state:STRING, zip:INT>
)
ROW FORMAT DELIMITED
FIELDS TERMINATED BY '\001'
COLLECTION ITEMS TERMINATED BY '\002'
MAP KEYS TERMINATED BY '\003'
LINES TERMINATED BY '\n'
STORED AS TEXTFILE;

The ROW FORMAT DELIMITED sequence of keywords must appear before any of the other clauses, with the exception of the STORED AS … clause.

Actually, it turns out that Hive does not currently support any character for LINES TERMINATED BY … other than '\n'

Schema on Read
--------------
In traditional way(RDBMS), Before storing data, a schema is created for a data before it is written into the database. So suppose we create a Schema consisting of 10 Columns and we try to load data which could satisfy only 9 columns that data would be rejected because of Schema on write, here the data is read against schema before it is written to the database.
The main advantages of RDBMS are that its Query response time is immediate and precision.

With HIVE, we have Schema on read, which means the data is not verified before loading but rather when a query is issued, here we have very fast initial load as the data is not read. 

So what if the schema doesn’t match the file contents? Hive does the best that it can to read the data. You will get lots of null values if there aren’t enough fields in each record to match the schema. If some fields are numbers and Hive encounters nonnumeric strings, it will return nulls for those fields. Above all else, Hive tries to recover from all errors as best it can.

Below info taking from Net
---------------------------
When we load the data our schema is checked, suppose we have 10 columns but data is loaded using 9 columns then schema is rejected. If first column is of INT type but first column of data is String type, then schema is rejected. This is called as schema on write, which means when we are writing the data at that time schema is enforced.

Hive supports Schema on read, which means data is checked with the schema when any query is issued on it. This is similar to the HDFS Write operation, where data is written distributedly on HDFS because we cannot check huge amount of data.

We cannot check each and every record of it as it will take months to check each and every record. This operation is fast and also improves performance.
                                               